♪ ♪
NEIL DEGRASSE TYSON:
Yes, this is home.
This is Earth.
Having trouble finding
a familiar continent?
The past is another planet.
Actually, many.
I'm standing on the great
expanse of time that has elapsed
since the Big Bang.
In order to think about it,
we've compressed it all
into a single year.
It's the early morning
of December 23
on this Cosmic Calendar of ours,
or about 350 million years ago,
when our world was
a mere four billion years old.
Earth looks so different.
You might not
even know the place.
The stars wouldn't help you.
Even the constellations would
have been different back then.
The dinosaurs were still
more than 100 million years
in the future.
There were no birds,
no flowers.
And the air was different, too.
The atmosphere had more oxygen
than at any other time
in Earth's history,
before or since.
This allowed insects to grow
much larger than they do today.
How?
Insects don't have lungs.
Life-giving oxygen is taken
in through openings
in the outside of their bodies
and transported
through a network of tubes.
If an insect were too large,
the outer reaches of these tubes
would absorb all the oxygen
before it could ever get
to its internal organs.
But during
the Carboniferous Period,
the atmosphere had almost twice
the oxygen as today.
Insects could then grow
much bigger
and still get enough oxygen
in their bodies.
That's why the dragonflies here
are as big as eagles
and the millipedes
the size of alligators.
So why was there
so much oxygen back then?
It was produced
by a new kind of life.
♪ ♪
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
DEGRASSE TYSON: What kind of
life could've changed
the Earth's atmosphere
so dramatically?
Plants that could reach
for the sky--
trees.
In their competition
for sunlight,
trees evolved a way
to defy gravity.
Before trees,
the tallest vegetation was
only about waist-high.
And then something wonderful
happened.
A plant molecule evolved that
was both strong and flexible,
a material that could support
a lot of weight,
yet bend in the wind
without breaking.
Lignin made trees possible.
Now life could build upward.
And this opened
a whole new territory,
a three-dimensional matrix
for communities
far above the ground.
Earth became
the Planet of the Trees.
But lignin had a downside:
it was hard to swallow.
When nature's demolition crew,
the fungi and bacteria,
tried to eat anything
with lignin in it,
they got a really bad case
of indigestion.
And termites wouldn't evolve
for at least
another 100 million years.
What to do
with all those dead trees?
It took the fungi and bacteria
millions of years
to evolve the biochemical means
to consume them.
Meanwhile, the trees just kept
springing up,
dying, falling over
and getting buried by the mud
that built up over eons.
Eventually, there were
hundreds of billions of trees
entombed in the Earth,
buried forests
all over the Earth.
What possible harm
could come from that?
(waves crashing in distance)
This cliff in Nova Scotia
is another kind of calendar.
It tells the story
of that other world
that once flourished right here.
And this is the death mask
of that 300 million-year-old
tree.
It was cast by minerals
that replaced the original wood
cell by cell--
in other words, a fossil.
The tree surrendered
its organic molecules
to the environment long ago,
its carbon and water.
Only its shape remains.
When this tree was alive,
it took in carbon dioxide
and water and used sunlight
to turn them
into energy-rich organic matter.
The tree gave off oxygen
as a waste product.
That's what trees
and other plants still do.
When plants die, they decay,
and this reverses
the transaction.
Their organic matter combines
with oxygen
and decomposes,
putting carbon dioxide
back into the air.
This balances the books
for the chemistry
of Earth's atmosphere.
But if the trees are buried
before they can decay,
two things happen...
they take the carbon
and stored solar energy
with them
and leave the oxygen behind
to build up in the atmosphere.
That's what happened
around 300 million years ago.
There was an oxygen surplus.
That's how the bugs got so big.
And what became
of all that buried carbon?
It lay there for eons
before dealing life on Earth
its most devastating blow
of all time.
There are places on this planet
where you can walk through time
and read the history
written in the rocks.
This beach in Nova Scotia
is one of them.
Every layer is a page.
Each one tells the story
of a flood,
one after another,
over millions of years.
The layer cake of flood
deposits was slowly buried
and turned into rock
by heat and pressure.
The same forces
that built mountains
then tilted and uplifted them,
along with the entombed
fossil forest.
The newer layers were always
deposited on top
of the older ones.
All the pages are
in the correct order,
bearing witness
to what happened here
over millions of years.
Back that way
lies the more distant past.
And with every step I take,
I move about 1,000 years
closer to the present
and away from the world
of 300 million years ago.
50 million years later
lies that way.
This was the beginning of
the end of the Permian world,
an event of unequalled carnage.
The Permian
is the darkest corridor
in this memorial to the broken
branches on the Tree of Life--
the Halls of Extinction.
Death has never come so close
to reigning supreme
on this world
in the quarter billion years
since.
The eruptions,
in what is now Siberia,
lasted for hundreds
of thousands of years.
The lava flooded and buried more
than a million square miles.
This event dwarfs
any volcanic eruption
in historical times.
_
Huge quantities
of carbon dioxide came pouring
out of the volcanic fissures.
This greenhouse gas
warmed the climate.
And this is where
the long-buried forests
of the earlier Carboniferous
Period reenter the story.
During the intervening
50 million years,
those trees had turned
into immense deposits of coal,
and as it happened,
one of the world's largest
accumulations of coal
was buried right there
in Siberia.
The heat from the lava
baked the coal,
driving methane and sulfur-rich
gases out of the ground.
They were laden
with toxic
and radioactive ash particles--
coal smoke.
This witch's brew
polluted the atmosphere
and radically destabilized
Earth's climate.
A sulfuric acid haze
blocked incoming sunlight
and darkened the planet.
Global temperatures plummeted
to subfreezing.
During lulls in the eruptions,
the acid haze fell back
to the surface.
But the carbon dioxide remained
and built up in the atmosphere
to cause global warming.
Years of frigid cold
alternating with millennia
of stifling heat
battered a dwindling population
of plants and animals.
They had no chance
to adapt to the drastic swings
in climate.
As the global warming
continued, the surface
and the bottom waters
slowly mixed,
raising the temperature
of the once-frigid depths
of the sea floor.
Methane-rich ices
that had been frozen in
the sediments began to melt.
Newly liberated methane gas
made its way to the surface
and into the atmosphere.
Methane traps heat
far more efficiently
than carbon dioxide,
so the climate
got even hotter.
And the methane also destroyed
the ozone layer
in the stratosphere.
The natural sunscreen
that protects life
from deadly ultraviolet rays
was eaten away.
The circulatory system
of the world ocean shut down.
These stagnant waters
became oxygen-starved,
killing almost all
the fish in the sea.
But one kind of life flourished
in this brutal environment...
bacteria that produced
deadly hydrogen sulfide gas
as a waste product.
That was the last straw.
The poison gas killed almost
all the remaining plants
and animals on the land.
This was the Great Dying.
The closest life on Earth
has ever come to annihilation.
Nine in ten
of all species perished.
It took a long time
for life to bounce back.
For a few million years,
Earth could have been called
the Planet of the Dead.
We are descended
from one of the few species
that managed to squeak by.
You are human and alive
at this very moment
because they managed
to endure, conveying
their DNA through one of
the most treacherous periods
in the history of life.
DEGRASSE TYSON: This mountain
was made entirely by life.
The life that flourished
back in the glory days
of the Permian,
before all hell broke loose.
This is part
of the 400 mile-long
Guadalupe Mountain chain
that runs through
Texas and New Mexico.
It's the world's
largest fossil reef.
All this was once
a great inland sea.
The reef flourished and grew
for millions of years,
and was home to multitudes
of sponges, green algae,
and animals too small to see.
When these creatures died,
they sank to the bottom
and were buried in the silt.
Over millions of years,
their remains were converted
into oil and gas.
Eventually, the basin
silted in and the reef died.
This marine ghost town
was then buried
a mile beneath the surface.
Later, tectonic forces
lifted the skeletal reef
high above sea level,
where it was eroded and sculpted
over eons by wind and rain.
Just imagine what
this place looked like
275 million years ago,
when it was a vibrant,
tropical inland sea,
dotted with islands
and brimming with life.
Until about
220 million years ago,
New England and North Africa
were next-door neighbors.
There was no such thing
as the Atlantic Ocean.
Those thin blue fingers
at the center-- they were lakes.
They were the first outward
signs that the supercontinent
was splitting apart and that
life on Earth was due
for another big shake-up.
A million years later,
the lakes became a long bay,
which would grow
into the Atlantic Ocean.
These profound changes
at the surface
were merely symptoms of a drama
that was unfolding far beneath,
in the depths of the Earth.
By the time we got here,
the telltale traces
of global upheaval were buried
at the bottom
of the deep blue sea.
We were completely cut off
from the great story
of Earth's violent past--
a species of amnesiacs
trying to find out
who we were and what happened
before we awakened.
In 1570, Abraham Ortelius
created the first
modern world atlas,
reflecting on the discoveries
of the previous 80 years--
the Golden Age of Exploration.
Before the ink was dry,
Ortelius stepped back
from his masterpiece
and became the first of many
to notice the striking
puzzle-piece fit
between the continents
on either side of the Atlantic.
He later wrote that the
Americas were torn away
from Europe and Africa
by earthquakes and floods.
But Ortelius's observation
remained nothing more
than a hunch
for the next
couple of centuries...
until an early 20th century
German astronomer
and meteorologist
amassed the evidence
to build the
scientific case for it.
Alfred Wegener had been drafted
during the First World War,
but was wounded soon after.
As he recovered
in a field hospital,
he scoured scientific
literature
for clues to the Earth's past.
Years before,
Wegener had happened upon
an intriguing paper
in the stacks
of his university library.
It puzzled Wegener
that fossils of the same
species of a now-extinct fern
were reported to be found
on both sides of the Atlantic.
Even more curious were
the discoveries of fossils
of the same dinosaurs
on both continents.
In the early 20th century,
geologists explained
how life crossed the oceans
by imagining that land bridges
had once existed between them.
It was thought that these land
bridges gradually disintegrated
and vanished
beneath the waves long ago.
But there was one piece of
evidence that convinced Wegener
that the prevailing
scientific view must be wrong...
the Earth itself.
Why would a mountain range
cross the oceanic divide
to continue
on another continent?
And why would you find
the same unique pattern
in the layers of rocks in both
Brazil and South Africa?
And another thing...
under what circumstances could
tropical plants have flourished
in the frozen wastes
of the Arctic?
Wegener concluded
that there was only
one logical solution
to this puzzle...
There had once been a single
supercontinent on Earth.
He named it Pangaea.
So Wegener becomes the toast
of the scientific world, right?
Not exactly.
Most geologists ridiculed
Wegener's hypothesis
of continental drift.
They preferred their
imaginary natural land bridges
to explain away
Wegener's evidence.
How, they asked, could
a continent plow through
the solid rock
of the ocean floor?
Wegener had no
convincing answer.
He became the laughingstock
of the field;
a pariah at scientific
conferences.
(dogs barking)
Despite this, Wegener continued
to fight for his ideas,
conducting daring research
expeditions to gather evidence.
On one of these, he learned
that colleagues were
trapped on an ice cap
without food.
On his way back
from the mission,
he became lost in a blizzard.
A day or two after
his 50th birthday,
he disappeared,
never knowing that, in time,
he would be vindicated
and come to be viewed
as one of the greatest
geologists in history.
Scientists are human.
We have our blind spots
and prejudices.
Science is a mechanism
designed to ferret them out.
Problem is, we aren't
always faithful
to the core values of science.
Few people knew this better
than Marie Tharp.
It's 1952, and Marie is
patiently enduring the slights
of her fellow members
of the geology department.
Her degrees in geology
and mathematics
count for little with them.
Bruce Heezen, a graduate
student from Iowa,
has just returned
from a lengthy expedition
to map the ocean floor
using sonar.
(Heezen grunts)
Will you do something
with these?
Bruce, look.
It's-- it's all come together.
There's this giant rift valley
that runs through
the bottom of the Atlantic.
Aw, geez, Marie, come on.
This is just more girl talk.
You're not in enough trouble
with everyone here already?
This sounds too much
like continental drift.
You want to end up
like Wegener?
DEGRASSE TYSON: But Marie
would not be dissuaded.
Years later, when Marie and
Bruce placed a map of oceanic
earthquake epicenters
on a light table
over her seafloor map,
the earthquakes
fell right along
the rift valley.
This was the smoking gun
for Wegener's
moving continents.
Heezen now knew
that Marie had been
right all along.
Together, they created the
first true map of the Earth,
including the ocean floor.
We were at last ready to read
the autobiography of the Earth.
DEGRASSE TYSON: Let's take
the Ship of the Imagination...
to a part of the world
that has been off-limits
to all but a few of us.
Two-thirds of the Earth
lies beneath more than
1,000 feet of water.
It's a vast and largely
unexplored frontier.
Everybody knows the Alps
and the Rockies,
but some of the world's
most amazing mountain ranges
are hidden from view.
Below 1,000 meters,
we enter a world
where there is no sunlight.
Hidden in the darkness,
a world of wonders.
This is the longest submarine
mountain range in the world,
the Atlantic Mid-Ocean Ridge.
It wraps around our globe
like the seam on a baseball.
The past is another planet,
but most of us
don't really know this one.
We don't see the mountains
for the water.
This is the world that Marie
Tharp was the first to imagine.
The highest peaks of the ridge
rise over four kilometers above
the ocean floor.
There are sprawling mountain
ranges and canyons, too.
We've now entered
the Marianas Trench,
the deepest canyon on Earth,
more than ten kilometers deep.
It formed when tectonic forces
pushed the seabed
under the adjoining
continental plate.
More people have walked
on the Moon
than have ever been down here.
The pressure here is a crushing
eight tons per square inch.
Being this deep in the ocean
is like having 50 jumbo jets
stacked on top of you.
Yet even here,
life has taken hold.
The fact that sunlight
can't penetrate the deep ocean
doesn't mean
there isn't light down here.
Many underwater species glow
in the dark,
through a process
called bioluminescence.
Our long history
as land mammals,
denizens of the sunlit world,
hasn't prepared us
for the amazing variety of life
that evolution
has crafted in the deep oceans.
Since there's no sunlight
down here,
there's no photosynthesis.
That means there are
no plants to feed on,
and yet, even here, in a world
of permanent midnight,
there's a thriving food chain.
It begins
with a process
called chemosynthesis.
These microscopic creatures
have learned to eat
what's pouring out
of that vent...
a noxious compound
called hydrogen sulfide.
That thick
black smoke provides
the chemical energy
that makes life possible here.
Tiny crustaceans
eat the bacteria,
and the larger animals
eat the crustaceans.
One day, on some future Earth,
these mountains could very well
end up above the water.
Tectonic forces continue
to shape our planet.
The future
is also another planet.
It was a volcano like this one
that created the Hawaiian
islands millions of years ago.
We live on the crust
of a seething cauldron.
At the center of our planet,
there's an iron core.
It's nested inside
of a larger, liquid iron shell.
Wrapped over this is the part
called the mantle.
It's rocky but hot and viscous.
Like a pot of soup cooking
on a stove, the mantle
is churning.
What keeps it moving?
Two things... the heat left over
from Earth's formation,
and the decay of radioactive
elements in the core.
And this outer layer--
the crust,
where you and me
and everyone we know lives--
is only as thick
as the skin on an apple.
The mantle
drags the solid overlying
crust along with it.
The crust resists
because it's cool and rigid.
From time to time,
it reaches the breaking point.
When that happens,
the Earth quakes.
It's not because
somebody misbehaved
and is being punished.
It's due to random forces
that are governed
by the laws of nature.
Our sense of the stability
of the Earth is an illusion
due to the shortness
of our lives.
If we could watch our planet
on its own timescale,
in which big changes take
millions of years to play out,
we would see it as the dynamic
organism it really is.
(rumbling, crackling)
This is the world
of the late Triassic period
about 200 million years ago.
That little guy?
It's one of
our distant ancestors.
He lived in Newark, New Jersey.
Wherever you walk on Earth...
lost worlds lie buried
beneath your feet.
50 or 100 million years ago,
even the most
seemingly ordinary places
have been the scene
of epic change.
These Palisades are a monument
to the breakup of
the supercontinent Pangaea.
The sequence
of volcanic eruptions
that made these cliffs also led
to the next mass extinction--
the one that ended
the Triassic world.
But a catastrophic
extinction event for one species
is a golden opportunity
for another.
The Triassic extinctions
offered one group
that had been around
for a while
the chance
to take center stage.
The dinosaurs
had a good, long run
for 170 million years.
Back then, India was an island.
It crept northward at the pace
of a few inches per year
on its slow but inexorable
rendezvous with Asia.
Then, once again,
the molten rock beneath
Earth's surface
burst forth and flooded
a huge area of western India.
The knockout punch
literally came out of the blue.
(rumbling, whooshing)
Few animals
larger than a hundred pounds
survived the catastrophes
of the late Cretaceous.
The dust cloud brought night and
cold to the surface for months.
The dinosaurs froze
and starved to death.
But there were small creatures
who took shelter in the Earth.
And when they emerged...
they found that
the monsters who had hunted
and terrorized them were gone.
The Earth was becoming
the Planet of the Mammals.
And the Earth continued
its ceaseless changing.
This was once a desert
where nothing could grow.
It was a million square miles
of sand and salt,
far more hostile than
any environment on Earth today.
Daytime temperatures were
hot enough to bake bread.
And it was more than a mile
below sea level,
so the atmospheric pressure
was about 50% higher
than what we're used to.
It would be hard to think
of a more unpromising
environment on this planet.
Yet this was the basin
of the Mediterranean
five and a half
million years ago,
before it became a sea.
The Earth never
stops moving for long.
The natural dam
at the western end
of the deep basin
gave way,
probably due to earthquakes.
And the deluge began.
The torrential waters rushed in
at a rate 40,000 times greater
than Niagara Falls,
turning a vast desert
into the Mediterranean Sea...
in less than a year.
There were as yet no humans
to witness this enormous flood,
nor to admire
the beauty it created.
Meanwhile, half a world away,
a broad channel separated
North and South America...
allowing ocean currents to flow
from the Atlantic
into the Pacific Ocean.
Tectonic forces
gradually brought
these two continents together,
closing the channel
and creating
the Isthmus of Panama.
This reorganized the worldwide
pattern of ocean currents,
which, in turn, affected
the global climate.
In Africa,
the lush green forest canopy
gave way
to a sparser landscape.
Some species
that were highly specialized
for life in the trees
became extinct.
But the generalists, the ones
that could find a way
to make a living no matter what
life threw at them,
endured and evolved.
Our ancestors had once
burrowed deep in the ground
to avoid predators
who stalked the surface.
But when
the dinosaurs perished,
they emerged into the daylight,
and over the eons,
made new lives
in the branches of the trees.
They developed
opposable thumbs and toes
for swinging
from branch to branch,
across the broad canopy
of treetops,
where all their needs
were fulfilled.
They could also walk upright,
but only for short distances.
With so many trees around, they
didn't have to go very far.
But then it got colder,
and the trees thinned out,
broad grasslands sprang up,
and our ancestors
were forced to traverse them
in search of food.
You needed
a totally different skill set
to make it on the savanna.
In the old days,
you could sit
perched on your tree branch
and watch the big cats
from a safe distance.
Now you were playing
on the same dangerous field.
(growling)
The survivors were those
who evolved the ability
to walk great distances
on their hind legs
and to run when necessary.
(growling)
This changed the way
they looked at the world.
Hands and arms were no longer
tied up with walking.
They were free to gather food
and pick up sticks and bones.
These could be used
as weapons and tools.
Think of it...
A change in the topography
of a small piece of land
half a world away
reroutes ocean currents.
Africa grows colder and drier.
Most of the trees can't
withstand the new climate.
The primates who lived in them
have to seek other homes,
and before you know it,
they're using tools
to remake the planet.
The Earth has shaped the course
of human destiny,
but so has the invisible pull
of distant worlds.
DEGRASSE TYSON:
The planets have influenced
our lives,
but not in the way you think.
The gravitational pull
of Venus--
small but close--
and that of Jupiter--
distant but massive--
tilted the Earth's axis
this way and that...
and ever so slightly tweaked
the shape of its orbit.
This periodically altered
the amount of sunlight
falling on the edge
of the northern ice cap.
Sometimes it made
the summers there colder,
and the glaciers
advanced southward
from one year to the next,
grinding and scraping,
and crushing everything
in their path.
That's what we call an ice age.
At other times, changes
in Earth's axis and orbit
made the Arctic summers warmer.
And the melting glaciers
began to retreat.
Imagine how resourceful
our ancestors had to be
in order to survive these
radical changes in climate.
With each glacial period,
the ice sheets grow
at the expense of the oceans;
the world sea level falls
by more than 400 feet,
uncovering wide areas of land
along the edges
of the continents.
15 to 25,000 years ago,
there was a period
when the ice receded,
exposing a temporary
land bridge.
The gateway to the other half
of the planet swings open.
Bands of wanderers
crossed the land bridge
to North America
and parts south.
About 10,000 years ago,
the manic swings
of the climate and sea levels
came to a stop.
A new and gentler
climate age began.
It's the one we live in now.
When the great
ice sheets melted,
the sea rose
to its present height
and the rivers carried silt
from the highlands
to build great delta plains
where they met the sea.
On those fertile plains,
we learned a new way of life...
how to grow things,
to feed ourselves and more.
For most of us,
this meant an end
to a million years
of wandering.
The way the planets tug
at each other,
the way the skin
of the Earth moves,
the way those motions
affect climate
and the evolution of life
and intelligence--
they all combined
to give us the means
to turn the mud
of those river deltas
into the first civilizations.
There's nothing like
an interglacial period,
one of those balmy
intermissions in an ice age.
And the great news is that
this one is due to last
for another 50,000 years.
What a break for our kind.
Just one problem.
We can't seem to stop
burning up all those
buried trees from way back
in the Carboniferous Age,
in the form of coal;
and the remains
of ancient plankton,
in the form of oil and gas.
If we could, we'd be
home free, climate-wise.
Instead, we're dumping carbon
dioxide into the atmosphere
at a rate the Earth hasn't seen
since the great climate
catastrophes of the past,
the ones that led
to mass extinctions.
We just can't seem to break our
addiction to the kinds of fuel
that'll bring back a climate
last seen by the dinosaurs;
a climate that will drown our
coastal cities and wreak havoc
on the environment and our
ability to feed ourselves.
All the while, the glorious sun
pours immaculate,
free energy down upon us;
more than we will ever need.
Why can't we summon
the ingenuity and courage
of the generations
that came before us?
The dinosaurs never saw
that asteroid coming.
What's our excuse?
There's a corridor
in the Halls of Extinction
that is, right now,
empty and unmarked.
The autobiography of the Earth
is still being written.
There's a chance that the end
of our story lies in there.
DEGRASSE TYSON:
Congratulations.
You're alive.
There's an unbroken thread
that stretches across
more than three billion years
that connects us
to the first life
that ever touched this world.
Think of how tough,
resourceful and lucky
all of our countless
ancestors must have been
to survive long enough
to pass on the message
of life to the next
and the next...
and the next generation,
hundreds of millions
of times...
before it came to us.
There were so many
rivers to cross,
so many hazards along the way.
Predators, starvation, disease,
miscalculation, long winters,
drought, flood and violence.
Not to mention
the occasional upheavals that
erupted from within our planet
and the apocalyptic bolts
that come from the blue.
No matter where we hail from
or who our parents were,
we are descended
from the hearty survivors
of unimaginable catastrophes.
Each of us is a runner in
the longest and most dangerous
relay race there ever was,
and at this moment, we hold
the baton in our hands.
The past is another planet.
And so is the future.
Some 250 million years from now,
many geologists think
that the lands of the Earth
will be united once again.
All this beauty
will have vanished
and the Earth
of our moment in time
will take its place
among the lost worlds.
The great internal engine
of plate tectonics
is indifferent to life,
as are the small changes
in the Earth's orbit and tilt
and the occasional collisions
with little worlds
on rogue orbits.
These processes have no notion
of what has been going on
over billions of years
on our planet's surface.
They do not care.
Each of us is a tiny being
riding on the outermost skin
of one of the smaller planets
for a few dozen trips
around the local star.
The things that live
the longest on Earth
endure for only
about a millionth
of the age of our planet.
So, of course,
the individual organisms
see nothing of
the overall pattern.
Of changing continents...
climate...
evolution.
That we understand
even a little of our origins
is one of the great triumphs
of human insight and courage.
Who we are and why we are here
can only be glimpsed
by piecing together
something of the full picture,
which must encompass
eons of time...
millions of species...
and a multitude of worlds.
In this perspective,
it's not surprising
that we're a mystery
to ourselves and that,
despite our
manifest pretension,
we are far from being masters
of our own little house.
This new corridor
has no name above the entrance
to designate its epoch,
and we don't yet know
which failed species will be
memorialized within its walls.
What happens here, in countless
ways, both large and small,
is being written by us.
Right now.
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com